See courtship season or courtship period
is a time for interview and not
intercourse.
So tell the man
before you start having erection do you
have a direction [cheering]
and you before you start becoming honey
you better take warning so that that
there won't be catastrophe. What God has
designed we must not have it despised.
So we need to approach marriage. We must
hold marriage in very very good and high
esteem. That is the design. That is the
template. That is what God had in mind.
God's design for marriage. God's design
for marriage. God's design for marriage.
God's design for marriage. You see, if
we want to understand marriage,
it is good for us to go to the
manufacturer's
manual, which is the Bible, because God
is the one that instituted marriage.
Marriage is not a woman invention.
Marriage is a divine institution.
Marriage is not a human invention. It is
divine institution. It did not emerge
from our culture. It emanated from the
creator. It is not a product of
civilization.
It is a provision from heaven. From the
very beginning before the entrance of
sin and be before the rise of systems
before the spread of sophistication and
before the coming of technological
advancements
there was marriage.
God instituted marriage. So when the
earth was still fresh, when creation was
still pure, and when man had not fallen,
God himself formed, he framed and he
founded marriage. In the book of Genesis
2:18 from the New Living Translation,
Genesis 2:18 from the New Living
Translation, the Bible says, "Then the
Lord said, it is not good for the man to
be alone. I will make a helper who is
just right for him. I want all of us to
read it together. Then the Lord God said
it is not good for the man to be alone.
I will make a helper who is just right
for him. I need to say this. You see in
the scriptures we have two passages or
two chapters that are perfect chapters
in the Bible. Now those two chapters are
perfect because there was no Satan.
Satan was not introduced in those two
chapters. And the chapters are chapter
one and chapter two. But in chapter 3,
Satan came and that was where you have a
lot of distortion, a lot of deformities
here and there. But in chapter one and
chapter 2, there was perfection. That
was the design. That was the template.
So in chapter 2, God said it is not good
that the man should be alone. That was
before sin came. That was before Satan
came into the scene. So marriage was
God's idea. Marriage was not as a result
of the fall. Marriage was not an
afterthought as in when man committed
sin and God now felt that well let them
marry maybe maybe that will help them.
No that was the original plan God had in
mind. So before there was sin to corrupt
us, marriage was created to complete the
man. So before there was you know before
shame came into the scene God was ready
even to bring about marriage. So
marriage was designed for communion
before there was confusion to distort.
Marriage was established for clarity. It
was established for unity and it was
established for intimacy. So therefore
marriage precede the fall. It predates
the failure of men and determines the
divine order. Now in the book of Hebrews
chapter 13:4, the book of Hebrews
chapter 13:4, Hebrews chapter 13:4 from
the New Living Translation, Hebrews
13:4, I want us to please display. The
Bible says, "Give honor to marriage and
remain faithful to one another in
marriage. God will surely judge people
who are immoral and those who commit
adultery." Now, let's read together. 1 2
3 go. Give honor to marriage and remain
faithful to one another in marriage. God
will surely judge people who are immoral
and those who commit adultery. Meaning
that marriage is not casual. It is
actually sacred. Marriage is not common
is actually a covenant. Marriage should
not be trivialized. It should be
treasured. That is the organog. That is
the initial plan that God had. So
marriage is holy. It is not hol marriage
is sacred is not just secular. Marriage
is designed is not a definition or the
design of man. So it is a covenant.
Marriage is a covenant and not a
contract is a calling and that calling
is not just a convenience. It is
actually a commitment and it is not a
casual connection that you see around.
So when we understand that marriage is
God's idea, we will treat it with God's
honor. You see when we recognize the
divine origin of marriage, we will
respond to it with deep preference. When
we see it as being sacred, we will then
steward it with some level of
seriousness. So marriage must be
reverred. Marriage must be respected.
Marriage must be highly regarded. It
must be protected from perversion. It
must be preserved from pollution. And it
must be prized above passing passions.
Because what God instituted, we must not
have it insulted. Praise the Lord Jesus.
Praise the Lord Jesus. So what God has
designed, we must not have it despised.
So we need to approach marriage, we must
hold marriage in very very good and high
esteem. That is the design. That is the
template. That is what God had in mind.
So the divine design was that marriage
was God's idea. It was not an initiative
of any man. It is not a traditional
initiative or a cultural initiative. In
that book of Genesis 2:18 that we
started with, the Bible made or God made
a pro a profound observation. It was a
profound observation. It is not good
that man should be alone. It is not good
that the man should be alone. And also
in that book of Genesis chapter 2:4. You
see, don't forget though, Genesis 1 and
chapter 2, those are the two perfect,
you know, chapters in the Bible. So
everything I'm still talking about is
still about the perfect state of
marriage. So Genesis 2:4, Genesis 2:24,
the Bible says this explains why a man
leaves his father and mother and is
joined to his wife and the two are
united into one. I want us to read it
together. One, two, go. This explains
why a man leaves his father and mother
and is joined to his wife and the two
are united into one. So from here we can
see the definition of marriage, the
design of marriage. Now the first thing
is that marriage is a departure is a
departure. Leaving old dependency,
leaving your father, leaving your
mother. Then the second thing is that
marriage is a devotion cleaving to your
spouse. You have a spouse that you are
cleaving to. You are you are joining
yourself. And the third one is that
marriage is a union. I come again
marriage is a departure. There is a
departure leaving old tendencies behind.
Then number two, marriage is a devotion
cleaving to your spouse. And the third
one, marriage is a union becoming one
with your partner. So marriage is not
just a ceremony. It is not just a
contract. It is not just a convenience
but rather marriage is a covenant.
marriage. That was the beginning of
marriage. That was the design. That was
what God had in mind. Then there was no
sin. There was no Satan in the radar.
You know, that was the hidden experience
of marriage. You see, because marriage
in Eden was pure. There was no shame. It
was peaceful. There was no struggle. It
was purposeful. There was no
competition, no sin, no fear, no
dysfunction. This was God's perfect plan
for marriage from the scriptures. But
then we also need to understand that
what are the benefits? Because God had
man in mind when he was forming
marriage. When he was instituting
marriage, [clears throat]
marriage was for the benefit of mankind.
It was to make our life better and not
to make our life bitter. Marriage was
supposed to give us a blessing and not
to give us a bleeding. Marriage was
supposed to become a tonic for us and
not to make our life toxic. Marriage was
supposed to be a gain and not to leave
us with a pain. Marriage was meant to
make our life sweet and it is not
supposed to come with sweat. That is
God's organog. That was the initial plan
that God had in mind. So what are the
benefits that are equable to us when we
do it God's way? Now we're going to be
looking at the book of Ecclesiastes
chapter 4. Ecclesiastes chapter 4 from
verse 9 to 12. That will be my anchor
because I'm going to be using that to
let us know the benefits, the design,
how God want marriage to play out what
he had in mind when he formed and
formulated form the template from the
scripture. Now um Ecclesia 4 from verse
9 to 12. Ecclesist
from verse 9 to 12. Ecclesiastes 4:9 to
12. Let's read together. Two people are
better off. Let's read together. Two
people are better off than one, for they
can help each other succeed. Verse 10,
if one person falls
can reach out and help, but someone who
falls alone is in real trouble. Verse
11, likewise, two people lying close
together can one, but how can one be
warm alone? Verse 12. A person standing
alone can be attacked and defeated, but
two can stand back to back and conquer.
Three are even better. For a tree
braided cord is not easily broken.
Praise the Lord Jesus. Now, so when God
formulated Mar, the first thing he had
in mind was companionship.
Companionship.
That means that you are not alone. You
are not alone. The scripture says two
people are better off than one. Marriage
answers one of life's deepest need and
that need is not to do life alone. God
did not create us for isolation. He
created us for association. This means
that there must be partnership. Someone
to share your joy. Someone you know to
you know to to to always be with you.
Somebody to share life with. Someone to
stand by you when you go through the
tough time in life. Somebody whose
shoulder you can lean on. Someone who
can be a benefit to you that you too can
be a benefit to. You see in this life we
need someone. God has not created us to
go through life on a solo run. God
created us for connection. He created us
for association. You see when life hit
hard. For example, maybe when you lose a
job or you lose someone or you have an
earth challenge or there is a tough
season you are going through in life. If
you have a godly spouse, that godly
spouse will not just sympathize, they
will stabilize you because that is what
companionship that is the essence of
marriage. You see, your partner will
hold you in the hand and tell you we're
going to go through this together. I'm
not going to allow you to go through
this alone. We are in this together.
That is the essence of marriage for
partnership. You so because you move
from loneliness to linkage. You move
from isolation to interaction from
solitude then to support. That is the
first reason why God formulated. The
second reason why there is marriage is
for marriage to be a complimentary.
Marriage was supposed to complement.
Everybody say compliment.
You see marriage is meant to complement
you. To complement you. It is meant to
make you stronger. The scripture says in
the book of Genesis 2:18 that I will
make a helper who is just right for him.
So marriage is not about duplication. It
is about completion. God did not
duplicated another Adam. What God did
was to create Eve. Different entity.
That is why marriage is not between Adam
and Steve. It is not between Eve and
Evelyn. Marriage is between Adam and
Eve. There was no it was not a
duplication. It was a complete you know
a a completion another entity another
human being to come and be a blessing to
you because what one person lack the
other person supplies. So what this
simply means is that you have different
strengths you have different perspective
to life and you have different graces
now coming together. So that person is
not just all by himself. He has somebody
who is quite different so that they can
go through life and then become better
because when they form or when these
differences come together it become a
strength. So for example maybe one of
the spouse is a visionary the other
person can actually be a detailed
person. Maybe one is a talkative the
other one can be the one that will not
talk too much. Maybe one like to be
physical is charismatic the other one
can choose not to be charismatic. And
you see when the two of them blend
together that is the beauty of life.
That is the beauty of life. You don't
want somebody who will come and compete
with you. You want somebody to complete
you. Because together when these two
different people come together, they
become stronger. They become wiser and
they become better. No competition but
completion. No rivalry but
reinforcement. Not clashing but a
complimention that comes to each other.
That is the essence of marriage. So the
third reason for marriage that God had
the mind. The third one is for
cooperation. Everybody say cooperation.
In cooperation they achieve more. There
is a cooperation. You know where we read
Ecclesiastes 4:10 says that if one
person falls the other can reach out and
help the other can reach out and help.
So there is a cooperation. Marriage
multiplies our effectiveness. Marriage
multiplies our effectiveness.
One can do something but when two people
come together they do more. The Bible
say that one can chase a thousand but
two will put 10,000 to fly. So there is
a lot of multiplicity that comes into
play. There is a cooperation and what
this simply means is that there is
shared responsibility. There is shared
vision and there is shared victory. For
example, because you have your partner,
you can start building a home together.
You are building a happy home together.
You are raising your children together
and you are pursuing your purpose in
life together. You see, when this is
done together, the burden of life
becomes lighter and then the results
become greater. In fact, you achieve
astronomical increase and you know and
success because there is a cooperation.
You are not doing it all by yourself.
you are doing with your partner who is
different from you because that person
is supplying what is lacking in you and
the picture is always better than when
it is done by you alone and it helps you
to move from effort to efficiency. It
helps you to move from struggle to
synergy. It helps you to move from labor
then to leverage. You leverage the
strength of your partner and that the
corporation will make the beauty of the
marriage to come out. Now what is the
fourth reason why God instituted
marriage? The fourth reason is that
marriage is for covering. Everybody say
covering.
>> Everybody need a covering in life. When
you are covered, you are protected. When
you are covered, you are secured. When
you are covered, then you are sure that
no matter what life throws at you, you
are defended because you have a cover.
You see, the scripture says in that
Ecclesia 4:12 that a cord of three
strands is not easily broken. Marriage
is not just about two people. is not
just the coming together of two people.
There is a third person there and that
is God. That is God. You see, the
scripture says that he that finds a wife
has found a good thing and obtain favor
from God. It's as if when you are alone,
there's a dimension of God that you
have. But once you get married, there's
an increased dimension of God that you
have because it came from God. So
marriage opens you up to some things
that you will not actually have if you
are not married. Those who are married
can attest to that. There's a dimension
of grace. There's a dimension of favor.
There's a dimension of help you receive
because you are married because it
offers you a cover. It offers you a
cover because the scripture says that a
three cold um a the a cord of three
strands is not easily broken. So you are
not just one person. You have now become
three. You and your partner with God you
become three and that will never be
easily broken. So now what that simply
means is that there is a spiritual
covering, there is an emotional safety
and there is a relational stability that
you enjoy. So in times of temptation, in
times of discouragement, in times of
confusion, a godly spouse will become a
voice of wisdom to your hearing. A godly
spouse will become a shield of strength
to you. A godly spouse will become a
reminder of God's truth. So marriage
becomes a covering never a crack.
Marriage becomes a covering for you and
not a crack. Now what is the intention
of God for marriage? The fifth reason.
Now the fifth reason why God insisted
marriage is for continuity. Everybody
say continuity.
God want us to leave a legacy. God want
us to leave a legacy. For continuity.
Because when God blessed Adam and said
go and multiply, replenish the earth and
subdue it and have dominion. What God
had in mind is not just for him to just
you know you know just for him to think.
No, God wanted him to continue life. God
said be fruitful and multiply. God is
you know marriage is God's design. God
marriage is God's design of a family.
God wants a family. Somebody said God
will put you in a family because of an
enemy. And it is too late for you now to
begin to say you don't want to have an
enemy. You already have one. The fact
that you are born you have one
especially when you give your life to
Jesus the moment you give you you you
you raise your hand up in surrender to
Jesus Satan automatically become your
enemy so it is too late but now say you
don't want to have an enemy but then
there is a family God gives you a family
because of an enemy so because of that
God there must be continuity God wants
you to leave a legacy God wants you to
leave a lasting legacy for the next
generation so marriage is God's system
for family for legacy and for
generational impact. God simply wants us
to raise children who have values. God
wants us to pass on the faith. He want
us to pass on the principles that we
have received. God want us to build
something that will outlive our earthly
existence. So a home is then a place
where love is modeled. A home is a place
where discipline is taught. A home is a
place where God is honor and where Jesus
is at the center stage of what they do
there. So such a home produces children
who know God. It produces children who
live right. It produces children who
lead well. So marriage is not just for
now. Marriage helps us even to affect
the next generation. Praise the Lord
Jesus. Praise the Lord Jesus. Now what
is the reason or what is the reason for
marriage? The sixth reason is for
consumation. Everybody say consummation.
Now this was expressly you know thought
on Sunday. Maybe I should because we
have children here don't let me go in
depth. You see for consumation you see
God want you to express intimacy rightly
within the confine of your marriage. See
God created us as sexual beings. There
is no amount of prayer you can pray. I
have tried it before. Yes. Growing up as
a young man in my secondary school I
think I was probably in my GSS classes.
I just started to have some funny
feelings. Ah, I began to pray. I fasted.
I fasted. I prayed. God, take this
feelings away. Take and I was keeping it
to myself because I did not I wasn't so
sure if if what I was feeling if other
guys were feeling those things. So, I
had to keep it private. You know, I
prayed and prayed, God, what is wrong
with me? And then there was a particular
girl in my class
very you know this girl did not even
know I existed but I I I I was I was
terrorized you know emotionally
you know this this see I actually prayed
I fasted but the problem was that each
time after the prayer and fasting once I
get to school I will open my book like
I'll be seeing her in my book I will go
to church when the pastor is preaching
if I open my Bible I'll be seeing her in
the Bible
Praise the Lord Jesus. You know, thank
God for the deliverance and the
deliverance was just the truth that I
heard and I know that what we are
hearing now is setting somebody free in
the name of Jesus. So for consummation,
God created marriage because you see
that that emotion that you have, it
wasn't you that put it there. It was God
and it's meant to be expressed and it
can only be expressed rightly in the
confine of marriage. Sex is an explosive
force. You cannot handle it not until
when you are ready and you are not ready
not until when you are married and that
is why we God made see if God just
imagine that God put the emotion there
and God did not permit us to marry then
God would not have said we have seen
again because he you have not given us
the permission to express what you have
given to us but for the sake of God and
for the fact that God is not just a wise
God is wisdom personified God made
marriage available so that we can
express this in the confine of marriage.
So the Bible says that in the book of 1
Corinthians 7:3 1 Corinthians 7:3 the
Bible say the husband should fulfill his
wife's sexual needs and the wife should
fulfill her husband needs as well. So
marriage provides a safe sacred space
for intimacy.
What this simply means is that there is
emotional bonding, there is a physical
connection and there is a covenant
expression in the confine of marriage.
So instead of confusion, instead of
living in guilt and misuse of our
sexuality, marriage provides us the
clarity, it provides us the purity and
provides us the security that we need.
Now what is the essence of marriage? Why
did God created marriage? The seventh
point or the seventh reason why God
insisted marriage was because God want
us to have character development.
Everybody say that character.
God want us to grow into maturity.
Marriage will reveal you and refine you.
You know, marriage will teach you
patience. It will teach you forgiveness.
It will teach you humility. It will
teach you sacrifice. You know, you may
think that you are patient. Not until
when you are married. Yes. But the
marriage will reveal, it will give you
your scorecard. Then you will know that
you actually work in progress. You see,
you may think you are selfless until you
must consistently consider another
person. And you know the funny thing is
that this person that you are married to
is just like you. You are not perfect
and that person too is not perfect. Let
us now assume that that person is
perfect. The moment they marry you, that
person also become imperfect and you too
you will you will use your own
imperfection to make the perfection of
that person to become imperfect.
[laughter]
So, so but marriage in marriage your
character will be built you know it will
built you see because marriage will then
become a mirror that shows you you it
will show you who you are to yourself
and it will become a furnace that shapes
you to become a better person. Now we've
seen what God had in mind the blueprints
the design the design that was in
Genesis 1 and Genesis 2. But in Genesis
3, something happened. Satan came and
sin came into the scene. And what
happened? The design that was perfect
became distorted.
So what we now have? We have ideal and
we now have reality.
Now we I'm going to tell us what
marriage is not as a result of the
distortion that came about from Genesis
chapter 3. We are going to see what
marriage is not because we need to know
because in Genesis 3 sin entered self
the place surrender and everything
shifted at that moment in the book of
Genesis. Okay, let's read Genesis 3:7.
Genesis 3:7 Genesis 3:7 Let's see what
happened. Genesis 3:7. The Bible say at
that moment their eyes were open and
they suddenly felt shame at their
nakedness. So they stew fig leaves
together to cover themselves. Look at
that. Shame, guilt came about just
because of distortion because sin came
into the s. So from that moment marriage
moved from harmony to tension. Marriage
moved from trust to suspicion. Marriage
moved from peace to pressure. And God
said God, you know, put a curse on both
the man and the woman and every other
thing just because there was distortion.
It was not the correct plan that God
had. There was a distortion. Now I want
to quickly run through what marriage is
not. Because these days I see some
people, some Christians also confusing
the original plan of God with the
distorted one that the devil corrupted.
Some people are running with the wrong
syllabus. And we need to know what
marriage is not so that we can live
right and embrace the perfect one that
God gave to us. Number one, marriage is
not a prison of pain.
Marriage is not a prison of pain.
Marriage is not a place where your jaw
is jilled. Marriage is not a place where
your voice is silenced. Marriage is not
a place where your spirit is suffocated.
For example, a a woman wakes up every
day, every morning, walking on eggshell,
afraid of saying the wrong thing because
if she see anything that can trigger
anger from her husband, talking is like
is like touching a mountain that burns
with fire and brimstone. So in her own
house, she's doing the name of the
father, son, and the holy spirit before
she talks to her husband. That is not
what God had in mind. when insisted
marriage that is not marriage or when a
man is constantly being belittled
being told he's useless is that the way
your friends used to do it is that the
way your mates used to do it that is not
a marriage that is not what God had in
mind when he was bringing these two
people together or when the man is being
constantly compared negatively and the
emotion is being drained that is not
marriage that is emotional incarceration
God did not design marriage to imprison
us. He designed it to improve our lives.
To improve to make our life better and
not to make it bitter. Number two,
marriage is not a license for abuse.
Marriage is not a license for abuse. And
we have to be clear about this. Abuse is
not discipline. Abuse is not discipline.
Control is not love.
You must tell me when you leave the
office and as you come on that is not
that is not love. When you are being
micromanaged,
you are being micromanaged.
That is not love.
Violence is not leadership.
The scripture says husband love your
wife just as Christ love the church. Now
you see Christ does not slap the church.
Christ does not shame the church. Christ
does not starve the church. What did he
do? He sacrifice for the church. He
sacrifices for the church. So because as
as marriage is not, you know, it's not
an abuse. We must not embrace it as an
abuse. And we have so many examples of
abuse. You have physical abuse when you
know eating when somebody's eating you,
it turns you to a punching bag. If you
want to fight, you should go and fight
his meat. But now he doesn't want to
fight his meat. He's fighting you and
has turned you. You are supposed to be a
pillow that he hugs. But now he has make
you a punching bag. That is an abuse.
That is not marriage. That is not what
God had in mind when he said marriage.
Emotional abuse when you are being
insulted. Manipulation. Silence
treatment. There's psychological abuse.
When you are being gaslighted,
you know when somebody is always telling
you are the problem, you are the
problem. You you see you are just
imagining things. That is that is
psychological abuse. Or there could be
financial abuse as well where you are
being denied access to basic needs so
that you can be controlled.
This is not the plan of God. This is not
the best that God had in mind when you
marriage or when there's a spiritual
abuse. Well, what does that mean? It
means that when somebody's using Bible,
quoting Bible wrongly and say the Bible
say you should submit. Didn't your Bible
say you should submit?
And the Bible say didn't your Bible say
you should love me like Christ and
Christ died for the church. Are you
supposed to die for me? That is that is
that is an abuse.
See, any love that leaves bruises on
your body and your soul is not from God.
So marriage, the third one, marriage is
not a cemetery for your destiny.
Marriage is not a cemetery for your
destiny.
Marriage should not bury your dreams.
Marriage should not bury your gifts.
Marriage should not bury your calling.
When I was in university, there were
some sisters that they were vibrant for
God. But after so many years, I see some
of them now. And I am surprised because
they their life does not reflect
anything fire.
And it could be because they marry
wrongly. They marry a man that quenched
the fire and today they are no longer in
the reader. They are out. That is not
marriage. Something is wrong. something
is wrong. Marriage is not a symmetry for
for destiny. For example, a woman, you
are called into ministry or you are
called into leadership, but your husband
continue to suppress you. Stay at home
with the children. Stay at home with the
children. Come on. Staying at home with
the children is not bad. Get me right.
What I'm saying is that when it is
deliberately done to suppress you and to
make you not to answer the call of God
for your life, then it becomes something
that we need to treat because that is
not the plan of God. God has not created
you to to know to to put your own
dreams, your vision, your calling, the
call of God on your life to put it on
the back burner just because you are
married. That is not the plan that God
had in mind. So over time, over time
when a woman or when a man is undergoing
all this all this stuff, they become
smaller in themselves. They become
quieter and they become weaker. That is
not marriage. That is destiny
suffocation.
That is not marriage. That is not the
plan of God. That is not the original
design.
Because then the fourth one, marriage is
not a theater of torment.
Marriage is not a theater of torment.
Marriage is not where fear is your daily
companion. Marriage is not a place where
anxiety is your constant atmosphere.
Marriage is not a place where tears are
your regular testimony.
So every time you are always in torment
that is not the plan of God. That is not
the original design. That is not what go
what God had in mind. In fact to me that
is not marriage. That is emotional
terrorism.
You are being terrorized emotionally.
And that is killing you. Is killing the
potential that God has given to you.
Number five. Marriage is not a covenant
of silence.
Marriage is not a covenant of silence.
God has not called us to suffer secretly
and to smile publicly but cry privately.
You pretend everything is fine while you
are dying inside.
You are being told that you don't need
to ah you don't need to tell anybody now
what goes on in your marriage should
stay with your marriage. Why are you
everybody have their own keep yourself
don't tell anyone.
Silence may protect an image but will
later destroy a life because there are
sometimes you need to talk, you need to
speak out.
Wisdom speaks and healing will require
help. Number six, marriage is not a
religious burden to be born at all cost.
Marriage is not a religious burden
to be born at all cost. Marriage is not
a religious burden to be born at all
cost. Some people carry marriage like a
cross God never asked them to carry in
that way. They say I must endure no
matter what.
Christianity teaches us
commitment but it has not commanded to
it has not commanded us to be in
captivity.
God has called us to live in peace. So
if you are always in constant danger
physically and mentally,
that is not the plan of God. That is not
the best that God has in store. That is
not the best. Then number seven,
marriage is not a substitute for God.
Marriage is not a substitute for God.
Marriage cannot heal all your wound. You
need to understand that. Because some
people approach marriage as if they are
needy. As if they are sick. I am looking
for somebody to love me.
I am looking for somebody to what? To
love me as if something is wrong with as
if they are sick. So they looking for a
doctor to treat them. If you enter
marriage like that, you will always be
sick because something is wrong. Because
those who go searching for love have
only manifest their own lovelessness.
The loveless never find love. Only the
loving and they don't have to search for
it. And that is why you must understand
that it is only God that can fill all
the void in your life. Your husband
cannot do that. If you want to clap for
Jesus, you can do that please.
[applause]
God is the only one that can fill all
the void in your life. So you must not
replace your relationship with God. You
must not because you must understand
that your your identity is not a
function of your partner. Your identity,
your happiness and your worth is not
from your partner. Because if you allow
your partner to be the one to decide all
that, the moment your partner changes,
then you two will change.
So if the man that have been telling you
you are beautiful, you are beautiful and
you your your idea of beauty, your
identity hung on that the day you are
ugly.
Praise the Lord. Now that is not to say
that as a man you should not you should
not validate your wife. But I'm saying
is that as a woman much more than what
you hear, you better know that there is
a God and what God says about you is
what really matters. Praise the Lord
Jesus. Praise the Lord Jesus. So this
must settle in our mind that endurance
is not the same thing as enslavement.
Submission is not the same thing as
suppression. Love is not the same thing
as losing yourself. And commitment is
not the same thing as captivity. We must
differentiate them. But now that we have
seen the original plan of God
and we've seen what marriage is not, I
think I will not do justice if I don't
tell you how we can remedy because some
people are going through what marriage
is not in their marriage. So how can we
convert what marriage is not to what
marriage is? That is why we have Jesus
now. That is why we have a church.
That's what we want to go into right
now. So how can we remedy? What are the
solution? Because God is a God of
solutions. No matter how big the
problems are, God is here to give us
solutions. So the first thing, so
wisdom, I call this one wisdom. Wisdom
for winning in marriage. Wisdom. What
are the wisdom that number one?
Recognize what is wrong. Recognize what
is wrong. Before anything can change,
something must be clearly seen. You must
recognize what is wrong in your
marriage. Are you married? Rec. You see,
you need to understand that something is
wrong because if you don't, then you
will not be bold enough to correct it.
You and your spouse will not be bold
enough to correct it. So what does it
mean to recognize? It means you can
distinguish love from control. You can
design correction from condemnation. You
can separate God's design from woman
dysfunction.
So because what you don't recognize, you
rationalize. Some people are
rationalizing abuse. They make excuse
for their partner and they they they
have been love bomb. The the the person
has used love to bump them and they are
caged. They are emotionally terrorized.
They've been kidnapped emotionally and
they do not know and [laughter]
[snorts] you know there was there was
this time that we were told that some of
the sorry to use this some of these chip
you know keyboard girls they they were
married off to some of these their
capttors and some of them are so now
used to them that now they are married
them they don't want to get get freedom
some people have been so much used to
abuse to the dysfunction to the
distortion that they do not want the
redesign anymore. They conf they they've
taken the low life and that is not the
best. So you must recognize recognize
what is wrong. You must do that. Then
the second thing is that you must refuse
what is harmful. Refuse what is harmful.
Recognition must lead to rejection. The
scripture says in Romans 12:9 that what
is wrong hold tightly to what is good.
See what must we refuse in our marriage.
Number one, we must refuse abuse in all
form. We must refuse it. We must stand
against it. We must not make it a daily
occurrence. We must not be so so used to
abuse that it becomes a lifestyle, a
pattern in our home. Manipulation must
also be refused. Manipulation that is
disguised as love.
Then also we must refuse fear that
present itself as leadership. Daddy is
back and everybody run for cover. That
is not leadership.
That is not leadership. This is not
love. This is not healthy and this is
not acceptable. So refuser or yeah
refuser is not rebellion. It is it is
righteous resistance. Jesus himself when
he was here Jesus refused wrong
conversations. He refused wrong
expectations and he refused wrong
pleasures. Jesus was always refusing
something from the Pharisees and the
Sadducees. Jesus was supposed to be
love. He loved everybody. But with the
Pharisees and Sadducees was always
having confrontation because they wanted
to dish him abuse. But Jesus was always
refusing it. Jesus did not become a
doormat to anybody. So you must not
become a doormat to anyone. You must not
you must refuse it. And that's why you
must go for counseling. Something must
be done. It has to be fixed. It has to
be fixed. It has to be. So you must
refuse fear. You must embrace freedom.
You must refuse harm and uphold honor.
You must refuse control and choose
Christ love. Now the third thing you
need to do is to repair what is
possible. Repair what is possible.
Repair what is possible. Not every
broken thing should be discarded. Some
should be res restored. The book of
Proverbs chapter 20 verse 18 the
scripture says plan succeed through good
counsel. Don't go to war without wise
advice.
So what does repair require? If you want
to repair your marriage. See everybody
need to understand where you stand or
where you are. There's room for repair.
There's room for repair. So what does
repair require? It requires honesty. You
must confront the truth. My husband is
having a side chick. Confront it. You
don't need to see if you want to just I
don't but it's not the best.
It's not the best. There must be
honesty. Then there must be humility.
Admitting you know admitting wrong. The
partner that is wrong must admit that is
wrong because that is when they can be
helped. Then there must be help. You
must seek for help. Seek guardians. To
the glory of God. In this church we have
marriage counseling, we have family life
ministry. That ministry we have loads
and load of experts. They are trained.
Some of them are therapists. They've
gone through trainings and we have
counseling units in church where you can
go to where you can be counseledled
because you must not normalize what God
has not spiritualized.
You must not.
So and again you must set eld
boundaries. You must do that. You must
set ed. Now the fourth one, restore what
is broken. Restore what is broken.
Restore what is broken. You see, even
when there have been pain, God can bring
healing. The scripture says in book of
Psalms 147:3, Psalm 147:3, the Bible
says he heals the brokenhearted and
bandages their wound. You see, God
will heal the broken heart, but you must
give him the pieces, the broken pieces.
When you give God the broken pieces of
your past, the broken pieces of your
marriage, God can fix it together. And
with God, impossibility does not exist.
So God can heal. There can be
restoration. There can be there can be
emotional healing. There can be
spiritual revival or renewal. And there
can be renewed pattern and perspective
when you expose yourself to counseling
because restoration is possible. Because
your husband or your wife is having an
affair, that should not be the end of
that marriage.
Because somebody's cheating or because
some something that is wrong, that
should not be the end of that marriage.
You must at least give it a chance. When
your car is faulty, you don't just throw
it away and say this car is giving me
trouble. Especially in the Nigeria of
today, if your car is giving you trouble
the first time and you throw it away, I
don't know, maybe you have so much
money, but you know you if your car is
is faulty, you will take it to a
mechanic. Now, let us now assume that
the first mechanic you give it to did
not do a good job. Will you now say
because and you you will still not throw
it away. You will give it to another
one, another mechanic.
You know, even if that one is not
getting it, you will still give it to
another one. See, if you don't give up
on your mechanic, why do you want to
give up on your marriage?
You don't have to give up. Don't give up
because restoration is possible. Praise
the Lord Jesus. Then the next one,
reinforce what is healthy. Reinforce
what is healthy. Reinforce what is
healthy. The scripture says, "Let in the
book of Hebrews chapter 10 24," Hebrews
chapter 10:4, he says, "Let us think of
ways to motivate one another to act of
love and good works." Let us think of
love and good works. So, we must
practice kindness intentionally in our
homes. We must speak life consistently
in our homes. Uh we must create healthy
rhythms in our homes. Now the next one
is that we must rely on God always. We
must rely on God always. Provers 3:5
says that trust in the Lord with all
your heart. See, you cannot run your
home without God in the picture. Any
home where God is pushed out of the
picture is going to have an ugly scene.
So you must deliberately put Jesus into
the picture. It was not a coincidence
that Jesus performed the first miracle
in a marriage and he could do that
because he was invited. So every day
Jesus must be invited into your home.
You must deliberately give him a space.
You must give him a space in your home
because he want to wine and dine with
you. There are some things that you
won't be able to fix that Jesus is ever
willing to fix. And that is why we must
always give God room. And if you're a
single person here, you've seen what
marriage is not and you've seen what God
had in mind concerning marriage. So now
if you are going for if anybody comes
around because I believe God that this
month there'll be miracle of connection.
And please for those who have been
waiting on God, God has not forgotten
you. You see when God delays his coming
is because he want to come big. Yes, God
is going to compensate you for your
waiting because when God comes late is
because he want to come big. And I want
you to know that you don't need to rush.
You don't need to rush because rushing
into any marriage or into relation could
be a red flag. So when somebody comes
and the person want to rush you is a red
flag. Is a red flag. Somebody want to
rush you. Somebody is already want to
start touching your body. Ah that is a
problem. Is a red flag because see
somebody you are in a relationship the
relationship is not is not up to 3
months. The person is already suggesting
let us go to bed. Let us go to bed. See
courtship season or courtship period is
a time for interview and not
intercourse.
So tell the man
before you start having erection do you
have a direction
and you before you start becoming you
better take warning so that that there
won't be catastrophe. We need all this
and I strongly believe that God if you
if if you put God in the picture of your
home and as a single person God is not
going to leave you. You see one thing
you can be sure of is that God has your
best interest at heart.
>> You can be sure of that even better than
you do. So please don't take your life
out from the hands of God. Let God lead
you. And for those of us who are
married, God is here to help. God is
here to give us sucker. You see, like I
said, don't give up on your marriage.
Don't give up on your home. God is still
very much in the business of fixing
broken homes. And God is going to fix
every broken homes tonight in the mighty
name of Jesus. But then if you rely on
God, what is God telling you about that
marriage? Because you need to hear from
God. There are sometimes there are
sometimes that you just need to hear
from him. Because sometimes God will
tell you some things that it is only you
that we understand. People may not
understand. I need to say this. It is
not every counselor that can counel you.
See if you have kidney problem if you go
and meet a gynecologist he can try
everything he can but he won't be able
to help you because that is not his
specialty. It's not it's not because it
is just that is not a specialty.
So if you're having problem in your
marriage, please go and meet an expert.
Not every counselor is qualified to
counsel you. You just need to understand
that because I've seen that played out
several times. And you need to
understand that what you are going
through there is a problem. So there's a
solution somewhere. And God can link you
up to the right people. And that's why
in this strength like I said we have the
counseling you know the counseling unit
the you know the the family life unit
for those of you who are singles before
you enter into marriage please we have
premarital counseling please go into it
the moment the guy is trying to shade
you is trying to fasten thing like I
said there is danger and you need to
prevent that because the bible say a
prudent person foresee evil and he hides
himself may the lord god bless us all of
us in Jesus might name so I want us to
please stand to our feet right Now, I
want you to stand to your feet right now
and begin. I don't know what you are
going to tell God, but I'm sure
something has been dropped in your heart
now. And I want you to open your mouth
right now and begin to tell God where
you need fixing in your life. Tell God
that father, I need you to talk. I need
you to turn things around for me. If
your home is not having that peace of
God, speak to God on that now. Speak to
God. And you have, if you're a single
person, pray to God that father,
continue to walk in me. Begin to walk in
me. continue to do your work in me so
that when the right person comes I too
will be a right person to that person.
Let's begin to pray to God right now.
Pray to God that father I receive grace
to walk in your blueprint for my life.
Father I want to practice marriage God's
way. I want to do this God's way. Lord
God I am not going to fail. I am not
going to falter. It is going to be
according to your word to me in the
mighty name of Jesus. Lord I receive
grace to do it your way. Lord, I receive
grace to wait for you and I receive
grace, Lord, the courage to be able to
put this word into use in the mighty
name of Jesus. Father, for those who
have broken, those who are going through
challenges in their homes, Father, I
pray for them today. You, God will, we
heal them in the mighty name of Jesus.
Let every wounded heart be healed. Let
every broken places be restored. Let
every pain receive the balm of God's
grace. Lord God, those who have been
hurt, Father, I pray for healing. those
who have been offended, give them grace
to be able to forgive. And father Lord,
I pray for those who are who who have
challenges as a result of addiction in
their homes. Lord, I break the power of
addiction. And I pray that the love of
God that passes, oh God, every
understanding of men, oh God, will reign
supreme in such homes in the mighty name
of Jesus. My adventure, you are here
today, you have not given Jesus a space
[music] in your heart. That is always a
starting point. And I want to give you
the opportunity now. So if you know you
are not saved, you are not sure that if
Jesus come today, you are going to go
with him, I want you to please signify
with a wave of hand to Jesus. And if
you're online also, please I want you to
say this prayer after me. Say, "Dear
God, I accept Jesus into my heart as my
Lord and my Savior. Save me and write my
name in the Lamb's book of life." Let me
pray for you. Heavenly Father, I pray
for my brothers and my sisters who have
said that prayer to you today. Lord, I
pray you will save everyone. Let
everyone come to the knowledge of your
word. Write their names in the Lamb's
book of life and their lives will never
be the same again in the mighty name of
Jesus. So church, don't ever forget that
what God had in mind is the very best
for you. [music] There is a design for
marriage. Go for that and you succeed.
God bless you.
Day star raising role models.